<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document xmlns="http://maven.apache.org/XDOC/2.0" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://maven.apache.org/XDOC/2.0 http://maven.apache.org/xsd/xdoc-2.0.xsd">
	<head>
		<title>User guide</title>
	</head>
	<body>
		<section name="Introduction">
			<subsection name="What is anycode ?">
				<p> Anycode is a code generation plugin for Astah* modeling software. It exports UML models, packages, classes to any text files thanks to
					customizable templates written in Groovy language. It is designed in such a way that it does not depend on any target programming language. In
					other words, it's up to you to generate any source files, or even documentation.
				</p>
				<p> It also provides a "directive" mechanism, i.e. : a set of functions that can be called from a template and that performs specific code
					generation tasks. Some of them are provided out of the box (Java, JPA, Objective-C) but you can also define your own libraries.
				</p>
			</subsection>
			<subsection name="Why an Astah* Plugin ?">
				<p>
					Astah* is a user friendly and lightweight UML tool, that enables to design domain models
					<b>easily</b>
					. Moreover, it provides a
					<b>free</b>
					community version as well as a free SDK to extend it, based on Maven projects, thus making it a
					<b>highly customizable</b>
					software.
				</p>
				<p> Anycode aims to achieve the same goals toward code generation and these are the reasons why it is released as an Astah* plugin.</p>
			</subsection>
			<subsection name="How it works ?">
				<p>Anycode will ask you 3 things before generating source code :</p>
				<ul>
					<li>What is your UML model ? To answer this question, you just have to design packages, classes, interfaces through one or more UML Class
						diagrams.
					</li>
					<li>Where are your Groovy templates located ?</li>
					<li>Where do you want to generate your output files ?</li>
				</ul>
				<p>Once all the above is setup, you can perform as many code generations as you want, and modify your model and your templates "live". Indeed, one
					of the advantages of Anycode is that code generation supports hot modifications.
				</p>
				<p>Behind the scene, anycode leans on several loosely coupled components :</p>
				<p class="center">
					<img class="img-polaroid" src="../images/architecture.png" />
				</p>
				<ul>
					<li>
						<b>Plugin GUI</b>
						is responsible for getting user input (namely 2 directories) and giving feedback about code generation process.
					</li>
					<li>
						<b>Template Engine API</b>
						is an abstract API for generating template based source code. It launches template rendering but remains independent from the actual
						implementation.
					</li>
					<li>
						<b>Template Engine Groovy impl.</b>
						is the actual template engine implementation.
					</li>
					<li>
						<b>UML API</b>
						exposes UML Model.
					</li>
					<li>
						<b>UML API Astah impl.</b>
						wraps Astah API. It enables to use Astah API indirectly, so that anycode is not tightly coupled with astah implementation.
					</li>
				</ul>
			</subsection>
			<subsection name="How to proceed ?">
			</subsection>
		</section>
	</body>
</document>